Question here in the chat.
How do life cycle hooks like before destroy or destroy work inside the Composition API?
Yeah, this is a great question.
So if we look inside of our life cycle hooks, oh, do I have it all up already?
The way to think about it is that Composition API doesn't actually,
as much as we're talking about it as like a separate way of architecting your apps,
it doesn't break away from how the component works.
So the question here regarding like before unmount,
so basically destroy instead of destroy, think of it as unmounted.
All that stuff still happens at the end.
The only thing that's different about the Composition API is that it just happens at the very beginning.
It's still all that other stuff you expect when it comes to destroying stuff
that still factors into Composition API.
In fact, Composition API will continue to hit all these other life cycle hooks.
So just to answer this question a little bit more fully,
let me go to the Pokedex here that has the script set up.
So if in the event, you're saying, oh, well, this component, let's say,
let me put this side by side so we can actually see this together.
And then let me reduce that so it's easier to read.
So if you're trying to say that like, OK, I have this thing where like,
when the right before the component unmounts, I want it to do something.
Sometimes that's a thing before it's destroyed.
The way you would do that is you need a helper method.
And so we have, just as you would expect it to be called,
it's not called before unmount.
Because what we realize with conventions is that this is really a life cycle event.
So really, all of our stuff are prefixed with on.
Like you would expect for other events, on click, on key up.
Well, since this is a helper method for an event for life cycle hooks,
on before mount is what we would import.
And then we'll, sorry, on before unmount,
because that's particularly what we were talking about.
So we would say on before unmount.
There we go.
And then I usually like to keep my life cycle hooks towards the bottom, usually.
But expect you a composition API.
That goes out the window depending on how complex the code is.
So it'd be very clear that it's not at all a best practice,
just kind of what I'm used to doing from the options API.
So what we would do is we would call on before unmount.
And then it's a function that takes a callback function of what we want to do.
So in this particular case, you might be like, do this thing.
And then that's it.
You've done, essentially, what you would do on an options API,
you just define it at the setup level.
So the key thing, again, to remember is that composition API
does not take you out of the flow.
You're absolutely bought into the whole thing.
It's just now you can literally set everything up right here at this one step,
and then let it run from there.
Whereas as we saw with options API,
there is kind of a little bit more intricacy regarding do your setup,
then pass that into your options,
and then options can do stuff from there.
So it's a style thing.
You'll figure out what works best for you.
But what I've done in this workshop is try to present you with the different styles
so that you can get a feel for it and figure out what you want for your apps.
Hopefully that helps answer that question.
Question.
The composables.
Are they singletons that are around for the life cycle of the app?
Or if they're not being actively used by components on screen,
are they tossed away and then reinstantiated fresh next time they're used?
This is a good question.
All right.
So to context set, the question here,
let me go to the base counter,
is around the idea of these composables
and whether they're singletons and basically how permanent are they
in regards to the entire instance?
So because we're now getting into composables,
this means you are starting to get into scoping concerns
when you're talking about JavaScript,
which is why I was talking about the learning curve for Composition API.
It starts to increment a little bit when you start to think about this stuff.
So to give you an example of this, let's go back to that count store.
OK.
So like any normal JavaScript, what you can also do
is we can also instead create something called something like useCount,
that is a function.
And so when you do this, though, OK, and let's say we have const localCount
equals a ref of, let's say, 50.
And then we return newCount,
or though let me actually name this a little bit better,
globalCount and return localCount.
OK.
There we have that.
I think I did all this right.
Perfect.
OK.
So the thing I need to do is actually not have this.
This is more of like that sort of factory approach to composables,
where what you're doing is you're running a function that then has basically,
well, we're about to see shortly what it looks like.
It's easier to show than to explain this in its raw form.
OK.
So rather than useCount anymore, we get this function called useCount.
And so what we can do now is we can say inside of the function,
we're going to get the fact that we can do const.
OK.
Actually, I did not like the way I minimize this.
There we go.
CountStore.
OK.
There we go.
UseCount.
And then this is logCountStore to start.
Let's not even return anything just yet.
OK.
Do, do, do, do, do.
If we take a look at our console and refresh, do, do, do, do.
Oh, right.
OK.
Sorry.
It's still looking for newCount in here.
So let me go ahead and comment that out.
And then where's newCount?
Oh, newCount also exists here inside of userCard.
Let me disable that as well.
Not that userCard.
This userCard.
Yep.
And then this should be hidden too.
OK.
Now we're good.
So what we see here is that globalCount gets two different refs.
There's a local and a global one.
And so inside of here, if we return countStore to, like,
to expose it out basically once again.
And then what we can do here is let's do two different buttons now.
We're going to have the ability to, oh, right,
it's being referenced here.
So we're going to say newCounter here.
That's going to add an HR here so that's easier to see.
And then let me not clip the browser.
OK.
So what we're going to do here is we're going to say globalCount.
And that's going to be countStore.globalCount.
And then localCount.CountStore.localCount.
OK.
So this, what we're seeing here, matches up to what we have here inside of countStore.
Right?
So the difference here being that let's go ahead and add some functionality here
where if we want to go ahead and increment stuff, what does that look like?
So we're going to add a button here real quick.
And we're just going to write some inline JavaScript
just to make life a little bit easier.
Where globalCount will be incremented by 80.
So I'll just call that global.
And then we'll do localCount by 100.
Although let's make this just more jarring so that's easier, 10, 100 local.
Great.
So what we have here, we have the references to it,
but we're trying to mutate the count specifically.
And so one of the things we can do instead is because of the way they're scoped,
we could do the increment localCount here, for example.
And here is where we can say localCount.value plus equals 80.
Expose increment localCount like this.
And then since we have that functionality shared,
now what we can do is we can say,
do, do, do, count store.increment localCount like that.
Save.
Fresh.
You see our local is now changing.
The reason this is different is if we go back to our user card
and let's do the same thing where we import our useCount here.
And so then we say const count store equals useCount.
And then return count store.
And this time we'll copy this exact snippet over here.
So it's very obvious.
Save.
OK.
You'll see a couple of things here.
One, because of the way the function instantiates,
as you would expect, the localCount, like the component
for the base counter actually is holding its own version
of that localCount.
While over here, we can see that the user card has its own version
of localCount.
On the other hand, if we have a function here
that allows us to increment globalCount,
and then let's just, once again, globalCount.value plus equals,
let's do 1,000.
Then we'll go ahead and do increment globalCount.
Great.
Now when we go ahead and switch this out.
Global.
That's good.
And then we have this right here.
Save.
Refresh.
We have global changing.
And we have, sorry, we have local changing in the top.
Global changing both sides.
And so I know this was a bit of a long-winded answer,
but it goes to show that it basically comes down
to your ability to scope your JavaScript
as you normally would, as far as generating those.
I was quite through.
I was asking.
So let's say you hit a button that rendered different components.
Yeah.
So both the counter and the user card are off-screen.
Mm-hmm.
And then you re-instantiate those two components.
Does globalCount start over?
Or is that state held by the app in some way?
In that particular case, if the component is unmounted
and the view is already tracking the global state,
I would imagine the global state would stay,
but the local state would get re-instantiated.
That's what you should expect.
You can use it as a singleton for the lifetime of the app.
Mm-hmm.
Yep.
There might be some gotchas in certain situations,
but again, if you run into that, let me know.
We can always take a look at that.
But that probably would go beyond the scope of this.
Cool.
OK.
So I know there is a lot going on here,
but I wanted to kind of provide the full landscape for those
who aren't used to writing their own JavaScript modules
and to actually show you some of the differences behind what
happens when you use a function to invoke it
versus just exporting a constant and just give you
some different options there.